Vienna, a city of grandeur and
sophistication.
And at its heart, a museum with secrets
dark and strange.
A family curse,
an alchemist's magic,
medieval special effects,
and a priceless treasure that
disappeared.
Secrets hidden in plain sight inside
Vienna's Consttorious Museum.
Vienna's constricious museum is the
highest expression of European
architecture,
the perfect compliment to the treasures
on display.
The sheer number of masterpieces [music]
is amazing.
What may be more amazing is that nearly
everything was once owned by one family.
And we can meet them here in the picture
gallery.
These are the Hapsburgs, Europe's
foremost ruling family for 500 years.
They appear cultured, relaxed, and all
[music] powerful. But they didn't start
out that way.
Back in the age of chivalry, being a
Hapsburg emperor wasn't easy.
In this [music] era, men in armor were
not loyal soldiers, but freelance
warriors who swore allegiance to
whomever they chose.
The highest ranking Hapsburg, Maxmleon I
tried to convince knights to follow him
in part by impressing them with his
armor. [music] Maxmillion developed some
of the most amazing armoring techniques.
The fit and finish had never been seen
before. Not only that, he took it to a
level of fun. He developed facial
features within the helmets that had
never been seen before.
Andre Ren is an historical technologist.
>> Today he has asked curator Matias
Fafenbler to show him this piece of
Maxmillian's armor.
It is a breastplate like no other with
prominent gears and levers.
Their function and purpose is unclear.
Andre is fascinated [music] by this
strange mechanical armor and has a plan
to discover its secrets.
>> There's never been a successful attempt
to recreate [music] Maximleian's armor.
My dream, make that happen.
>> Matias shares this dream. Today, he's
giving Andre unprecedented [music]
access to examine the armor from every
angle.
Its exact purpose is still a mystery.
Matias and Andre believe that purpose
has something to do with jousting.
>> Jousting was the Middle Ages most
popular sport.
>> This was the football of its time, the
soccer.
>> This was the only great spectator sport.
Yes.
>> And Maxmillian created the [music]
biggest spectacle of all.
>> Yes.
For knights, jousting was a way to prove
their bravery in front of a crowd.
>> Both horses to combined with [music] the
armor, it's 1,500 kilos. This is like
driving a small car on a concrete wall
with 100 km/ hour. So, it's an enormous
force.
>> For Maximillion, the spectacle was a way
to attract potential allies to his
court.
The important thing were not the sport
events in themselves but the negotiation
which took place at the same [music]
time. So he tried to get more power by
winning over the knights.
>> The problem was every duke in the land
held his own jousting tournament.
>> So there was a competition between the
dukes, the middlesized rulers and the
emperor.
If Maxmleon [music] wanted to keep the
crowds coming,
he needed a way to pimp his joust.
And that might be where this breastplate
comes in.
Matias believes it once had a shield
attached to it that was designed to
break away on impact.
>> If you hit here, nothing happens. If you
have hit here, nothing happens. If
[music] you hit here or if you hit here,
nothing happens. If you hit here
and you have to hit hard, then this
mechanism [music] is unlocked.
>> As soon as that was loosed, yes, the
shield would go up into the air.
>> Andre intends to test this theory by
recreating the breastplate, [music]
fashioning a shield, and putting them to
the test in a jousting arena. His
workshop [music] near Detroit, Michigan,
has all the right equipment for the job.
But though he and his team start with
detailed schematics, the inner workings
[music]
surprise him.
>> I just assume that was art.
>> No, there's not a lot of art here.
Everything you see is the way it had to
be to exist. I'm really impressed with
ancient technology. Our ancestors were
incredible.
This is one of the greatest challenges
from historical reverse engineering that
we've encountered. It is really, really,
[music] very difficult.
Emperor Maxmleon spent a fortune
developing and perfecting [music] new
types of armor. And after 6 weeks of
intensive labor, Andre knows why.
>> Since we left Fienna, [music] we've had
four major revisions where we scrapped
everything. We've had 27 minor versions,
which is why we call this suit number
27. We have a thousand man hours into
just building this. I wonder how many
times [music] it took them to build the
same thing.
>> The 15th century design is full of
surprises.
>> We discovered that in the spring box,
there are two little ejector springs
that push the arms out. Other than that,
there's nothing in the spring box.
The system will be field tested by Andre
himself
along with his passion for historic
recreation. He is a champion modern-day
jouster.
>> Now look at this.
>> This this suit really encumbers [music]
me. I I can't move at all. Actually,
>> the breastplate is much heavier than
anything Andre has worn before.
>> Is that better?
>> It gained 28 lbs. [music] I'm really
concerned about safety, guys. I'm going
to tell you that right now. This makes
me very front heavy. If I do come off, a
ring master knows to [music] call 911.
>> Knights of old used heavy steel tipped
lances and were often injured in
high-speed collisions.
Andre and his opponent opt for [music] a
safer approach using balsa tipped lances
instead.
>> And we are ready to rock and roll.
Rotate in.
>> In a normal jousting match, a knight
scores by hitting anywhere on the body.
>> Here is your lance.
>> But to have any chance to make Andre's
shield break away, his opponent will
need to hit the tiny [music] disc at the
center.
>> Okay, I'm loaded.
>> Lay on.
>> This turns out to be a challenge.
Do it again.
>> The second hit releases the shield, but
Andre barely saw it through [music] his
visor, so he wants to see the instant
replay.
>> Here we go. Start of the run.
>> Yeah, that's not No. Too much work into
this
>> for that. [music]
>> Yeah,
>> we need to have it go over the head.
The team tries again, but the shield
flies no higher than before.
Andre is too exhausted for another
attempt. That was the single hardest
thing [music] I've ever done. Jousting
>> for Andre. The riddle is why the shield
didn't fly higher. The breastplate
worked really well. The breast plate's
[music] only onethird of the entire
assembly. So, the next step is to
recreate the shield and the lance. The
challenge is there's none left in the
world to go by. There's no drawings
really of them. So, it'll be an uphill
battle, but we'll make it.
>> Make fire.
>> Andre and his team get back to work with
a new respect for Maximleon's engineers.
They realize that armed with all the
right combination of equipment,
Maxmillion's knights [music] would have
produced an impact that looked more like
this.
and [music] one Maximleian a
welldeserved reputation as the host with
the most
at Vienna's Kistoicious Museum on the
morning of May 11th, 2003.
Security staff reported that there had
been a break-in during the night.
>> I went into the gallery. I saw this
broken showcase, the empty [music]
showcase, and I just had to burst in
tears. This was an incredible
catastrophe.
>> Missing was a gold statue known as the
Saliera, valued at 58 million US.
This museum secret is about how to catch
a thief.
It was a huge story in the public in
Austria. It's a piece of like of of of
the of the soul of this country and it
was gone.
The Vienna police assigned the case to
their chief investigator,
Detective Ernst Geger.
>> The day the crime was committed, the
scapole was like this. So the offender
could climb to the window where it was.
Here's the window.
He activated the alarm system. From now
on, every [music] second counted for our
offender. So he h heard it there,
smashed the glass, put out the salera,
and went back this way, jumped up to the
window, and escaped outside. [music]
>> Guyer noticed that the gallery was
filled with priceless Raphaels.
>> We asked ourselves, why didn't he steal
them? Just took out the salier. [music]
The most likely reason was that the
saliera is made of gold, easy to melt
down and [music] sell.
>> Since we didn't know who he was, we
didn't know how he ticked it. And so we
were very worried that he might destroy
[music] it.
>> But Guyer had a hunch the thief knew the
saliera was more valuable intact. We
thought somebody who knew about the
uniqueness and importance of the saliera
had stolen it.
The saliera is the only surviving gold
sculpture by Benuto Chelini, a prominent
Italian artist of the 16th century.
Famous for his creative genius and his
impulsive [music] behavior
during the sack of Rome. He was accused
[music] of stealing the Pope's jewels
and hiding them.
But whoever stole Chelini's masterpiece
had something else in mind.
Museum officials received a letter
demanding a ransom of $5.5 million US
and warning them to keep it hush hush.
>> It was clear it was an art naping case.
>> But before the [music] police could act,
the thief's letter was leaked to the
press.
>> From that moment on, there was nothing.
There was nothing. He didn't answer. Uh
he didn't write another letter. All the
communication stopped.
[music] Weeks passed, then months.
>> Every single day in such a situation
[music]
seems to be a very long time. I've
personally thought about that [music]
every day.
>> It was just gone. No trace. People
believed [music] maybe it's destroyed.
Maybe it's it it appears somewhere on
the black market. The police said they
are close to the solution. They're going
to get him soon, but they did not do it
for years.
>> In October 2005, nearly two years later,
we hear again from our offender.
The thief's second letter [music]
offered proof that he still had the
saliera.
It directed police to a spot near a
statue of Mozart, just a stones throw
from the museum.
Guyer felt the thief was playing with
him and perhaps even watching him.
This time there would be no leaks to the
press.
>> We did it very secretly, not with many
policemen, only plain clothes men. They
looked around.
They found it here behind.
>> The package contained a small gold
trident. The thief had pried it from
Neptune's hand.
>> All of a sudden, we realized there was
the big chance that we might see the
object again.
>> A week later, the thief sent a text
message from a cell phone that had been
modified to be untraceable.
He had doubled the ransom to $12 million
and wanted it delivered by Courier in
exchange for the Saliera.
Guyer sent a courier to the specified
location, but with no money in his
knapsack.
Police followed at a discrete distance,
ready to pounce.
The thief didn't appear. He sent another
untraceable message with a new
destination.
And then [music] several more.
These instructions were a kind of wild
goose chase.
At the last location, [music] there was
a long interval before a message
arrived. And when it did, the thief was
angry. The message said, "Against his
instruction, police was involved and
therefore he stopped it. And now it will
destroy the salera."
>> It seemed that the world would be robbed
of Chelini's genius, and Guyer would
never catch the brazen thief.
Unfazed by setbacks, Guyger had the last
message analyzed.
This time, the thief slipped up. He used
a cell phone with a traceable ID number.
He had no more prepared cell [music]
phone, so he had to buy one more cell
phone.
>> Guyer traced the phone to this shop.
The store had a camera trained on the
checkout counter.
When these security images were
broadcast by the media, they elicited an
immediate response.
>> A man phoned the police and said, "I'm
the man on the photo, but it's a
mistake. I didn't have nothing to do
with this Ala case." Robert Mang had no
criminal record or obvious motive,
but his job was designing security
systems,
so he would have known how to get past
the one in the museum.
At Mang's home, Guyger discovered
[music] the first draft of a ransom
note.
Confronted with this evidence,
Mang led police to a wooded area.
Buried underground was a lead box
containing Chelini's masterpiece.
>> So the salier was back. A piece of
Austria was back and Mr. Geger was
honored in the parliament as a hero.
>> Many wondered why a previously honest
man [music] would commit such an
outrageous crime.
>> This was a very very [music] strange
situation. Knowing that Chelini was such
an outrageous character, I had the
feeling that maybe the thief wanted to
to be the Chelini of our times.
>> When Chelini was arrested, [music] he
refused to admit he had stolen the
Pope's jewels, even under torture.
And one night, he made a daring escape.
By contrast, Robert Mang pleaded guilty
and would not get away. Instead [music]
of achieving the fame of a Chelini, he
ensured the fame of a Chelini
masterpiece.
>> Until [music] this very moment, only a
handful people in Austria knew about the
salera. But from this day on, everybody
know.
[music] For hundreds of years, Europe
was on the gold standard.
So if you were a king who wanted his
face on a gold coin, you had to have
some gold in your treasury.
In 1677,
Austria's emperor Leopold ran out.
Leopold was in a terrible financial
situation because of the extremely
expensive war against the Turks. So he
need a lot of money just to pay his
troops.
Then one day in November, a stranger
arrived at the palace with an offer to
solve the king's money problems for
good.
He said he would turn silver into gold
and then tell the emperor the secret for
a price.
The cashstrapped emperor agreed.
According to all accounts, there was no
slight of hand. A silver medallion
changed as if by magic into gold.
You might think alchemy can't be real,
but the gold medallion created by the
alchemist is in the constricious museum.
It's more than 7 kilos of gold. So, it's
the biggest gold medallion ever cast uh
in the world.
>> How did the alchemist do it? This might
be our most valuable museum secret.
The mystery [music] fascinates
archaeologist Marcos Martino Torres.
We know from the texts that this [music]
medallion was transmuted in front of the
very emperor. So, how is it that they
did that transmutation? Hopefully, we
can now find an answer to that question.
>> The first thing Marcos would like to
know is the purity of the gold in the
medallion.
Museum [music] staff can't provide a
definitive answer without damaging it.
But a non-invasive X-ray proves that
gold is definitely present.
How did the alchemist do it?
To look for the answer, Marcos travels
40 km north of the museum.
Here he meets archaeologist Sigret Van
Austin who has uncovered evidence of an
alchemist's workshop in a 16th century
church.
Alchemists were Christian mystics,
seekers of the legendary philosophers
stone, the power to turn base metal into
gold.
But in the back room is proof that they
did not put their faith in God alone.
>> But should we go inside? They can't
wait.
Several years ago, Sigret made an
amazing discovery beneath the floor.
>> So, this is where it all happened. This
is where you found this equipment.
>> It's only a little part of the
materials. We have more than thousand
[music] objects.
>> 1,000 objects. They've got an assortment
of material. Every one of them very
specialized for a [music] specific
technical function. You just have to
have a look at this to see. They knew
[music] a lot of science, don't they?
>> This laboratory was a high-tech.
>> Much of this equipment would look at
home in a modern chemistry lab.
>> When people at the [music] split think
about alchemy, of course, they
immediately think of Harry Potter.
We've tended to regard alchemists
[music] as wizards and obscure
philosophers.
But these alchemists knew a lot more
science than we credit them for. It was
[music] very much about trial and error,
experimentation.
So alchemists were really early [music]
chemists,
including the alchemist at Leopold's
court.
Marcos thinks he changed silver into
gold using a trick that only a chemist
would know.
He believes the alchemist's original
medallion was not pure silver, but a
material much like this, forged in a
modern lab by jeweler Jamie Hall.
>> Well, although it looks entirely silver,
there's 30% gold uh in this. Um I don't
think anyone would would realize it was
in there.
>> So, it's roughly 70% [music] silver, 30%
gold. It looks very silver.
And if the alchemist started with silver
that contains [music] gold, Marcos may
know what chemical was in his vat.
>> I've been looking into what may have
been available to a 17th century
alchemist. And I think the most
plausible reagent would be nitric acid.
>> Alchemists called it Aquaforis.
>> The name Aqua Foris says it all. It's so
strong that it dissolves [music]
anything you put in it. Anything except
for gold. So, we've got everything we
need except for an emperor.
>> You can see it's turning dark
immediately. It's obviously attacking
the silver.
>> After about 3 minutes, Marcos removes
the medallion from the acid.
>> It's come totally black. It doesn't look
like gold. Let's hope we can actually
[music] do something to it. So, we have
to rinse it quite well so that the
reaction doesn't continue.
It certainly [music] looks different,
but not quite golden as we would hope.
>> Yeah, [music] it still isn't taking much
off. So, what we're going to have to do
is use a brass brush.
>> Now, that is looking [music] very
impressive.
>> Now, that really does start to look
golden, doesn't it?
>> I think we've transmuted our medallion.
>> Yeah, we could be millionaires.
[laughter]
Marcos is sure that the alchemist
performed the same chemistry trick for
the emperor.
And because it was really just a trick,
it couldn't solve Leopold's money
problems.
Regaining the Hapsburg family fortune
would be up to his granddaughter, Maria
Teresa,
who employed an even more magical way to
get rich quick.
She printed paper money
inside the Constarious Museum. What
medieval artifacts are made of reveals
the era's pecking [music] order.
For the lowly foot soldier, wood [music]
and iron. For noble knights, the finest
steel. Kings are worthy of gold. And so,
it [music] seems is a falcon.
Hunting game with birds of prey was the
noblest of pastimes.
It's [music] very noble because you put
your will to a living animal and he's
doing the hunting for yourself.
A knight might hunt with a Harris hawk
while baronss favored the Eurasian owl.
But only this bird is fit for a king.
And modern falconer Dan Franken knows
why.
>> Jer falcons are basically [music] the
epitome of falcon. They are by far the
top end of the top end. They're like
driving a Ferrari. [music] They are
unbelievably quick and fast.
No king in history enjoyed falconry more
than Frederick II, who was crowned Holy
Roman Emperor in 1220.
Frederick's love for falcons would help
to bring an end to the Dark Ages.
The reason why is a museum secret.
Frederick came to power in an era when
the church decreed that the sun went
around the earth and science was akin to
heresy.
Asking questions about the universe
could get you burned at the stake.
Even emperors were advised to follow the
old ways even in the sport of falconry.
Like all medieval falconers, Frederick
calmed his captured birds by sealing up
their eyes.
>> Using a needle, they would take the
bottom lid of the falcon and the top
lid, put a [music] little tiny hole in
it, and put the two lids together. Now,
that these days is totally unnecessary
and a lot of people consider barbaric.
>> The same might be said for the way
Frederick trained his falcons to hunt
for him.
He lured them with live birds tied to a
string.
>> That's where you would tie it up and
then you could swing it as a falcon
[music] will see that it's a bird in
distress and they will go right for it.
>> After months of training, the falcon
would attack on command.
In 1226, Frederick was pulled away from
his favorite sport when the Pope ordered
him to lead a crusade.
There had been several previous attempts
[music] to take Jerusalem for
Christendom.
All had failed.
But as Holy Roman Emperor, it was
Frederick's duty to try again.
>> He landed with [music] an army in
Palestine, but didn't fight any battle.
He started to negotiate.
>> During the diplomatic talks, Frederick
became fascinated by what the Arabs
showed him.
astronomy and engineering far in advance
[music] of anything in Europe.
Frederick soon realized why they were
ahead.
They asked questions and then tested
them, what we would call the scientific
method.
Frederick also discovered a shared
interest. In the Arabic [music] culture,
falcon hunting played an important role
and still plays an important role. If
you go to the Emirates, you see lots of
sultans hunting with falcons.
>> For both Frederick and the Sultan,
falconry was much more than a sport.
>> The bond that you have between a
vertebrae [music]
and yourself is very similar that you
have with a dog, but you can't hug this.
But once both of those eyes lock onto
you, beautiful.
>> Frederick noticed that the Arabs trained
their birds a little differently.
For one thing, they didn't seal their
eyes with thread.
>> Originally, the Arabs developed the hood
to replace the ceiling because they
[music] thought it wasn't such a
wonderful idea.
>> Frederick tried the Arab method and he
tried the Arab way of questioning
things.
>> So, [music] it it goes on in this way.
I'm going to one, two, three do it like
that.
>> He tested the hood and found it to be
superior.
Frederick also noticed that Arabs didn't
need live birds for bait.
Making a lure from the wings and meat of
the prey worked [music] just as well.
It's supposed to follow what it is that
the falcon's going to be chasing [music]
in a natural environment.
>> Frederick tested this Arab technique and
many others.
His
interest in Arab falconry and science
created an atmosphere of mutual respect
between the two leaders
>> and this enabled them to negotiate a
solution which was good for both sides
and this was that uh the Sultan of Egypt
would give Jerusalem to the emperor and
the emperor wouldn't attack Egypt.
>> With the Sultan's blessing, [music]
Frederick was crowned the king of
Jerusalem.
His was the first and only bloodless
crusade.
When he returned to Europe, [music] he
published the results of his falcon
experiments.
It's the first treatise [music] on
falconry. It's it's kind of what we
refer back to. That's very important. I
mean, it's it it's the Bible.
Frederick's book revolutionized European
falconry [music]
and transmitted the scientific method
from the Islamic world to Christendom
where it would influence [music]
visionaries like Galileo and Leonardo da
Vinci.
The church was not pleased but it was
too late. Frederick and his beloved
falcons had already helped bring light
into the dark ages.
Inside the Consttorious Museum is a
violin that was made to play the music
that Vienna is famous for. The waltz.
This sublime waltz melody, the blue
Danube by Johan Strauss has become a
familiar fixture at many formal
occasions.
Today we rarely dance the waltz except
to observe archaic traditions. But if
you think the wal is tame or boring, it
isn't.
The truth about the wal and how it
changed the world is our museum's
secret.
The story begins at the end of the 18th
century when all of Europe was engulfed
by war and Austria had fallen on hard
times.
>> It was a poor time. very poor time.
People lost a lot of of members of their
family, soldiers who died in the battles
who were injured. Peter Vidhol is a
professional tener and president of the
Johan Strauss Society.
>> There was no time in Austrian history
which was too sad for the people to
forget music and to forget to dance.
Music helped the Austrians always to
survive.
>> To take their minds off the carnage,
Austrian nobles danced the minuette,
bowing and curtsying to each other as
they had done for centuries.
But in the countryside, commoners were
inventing [music] some brand new dance
moves.
To understand what was new about them,
we need to take it step by step.
Now you will see the way they are
standing already. The lady is right
slightly to the left and she looks to
the left. That's very important. And
then all you [music] have to do is
repeat six steps all the time.
>> Thomas Schaefer Elmire runs Vienna's top
dance academy. Vanessa and Peter have
never danced the walts before.
>> Gentleman starts right foot forward lady
left foot back. In [music] contrast to
the minuette, waltzing couples never
change partners and they stay much
closer together. [music]
>> The men must touch the woman not only
with the fingers on their hand but also
[music] at their waist. Yeah. There is
more contact with the body of the woman.
When you dance very quickly, a waltz,
then could be that the dress of the lady
comes a little bit up and then could be
that you can see her ankle or maybe her
curve.
>> In the 18th century, such wanton
displays were frowned on
>> and to that time it was nearly a
scandal.
>> So the church was not in favor of it and
the rulers were not in favor of it. The
church very often was against things
that that gave the people a lot of fun.
And so Europe's straightlaced nobles
stuck [music] with the minuette
throughout the long war and into an era
when all of Europe longed for peace.
In 1814, Emperor Francis I of Austria
decided to try something new. He invited
all the princes and kings and also the
tsar of Russia to vi to come to Vienna
to find a treaty and to draw new borders
for Europe. As the nobles negotiated in
this palace, the halls echoed with
shouts and accusations.
After long days of acrimony, they were
eager to unwind. The plan of the emperor
during the Venice Congress was to make a
lot of amusements for the European kings
and princes. There were a lot of balls
and concerts and and different events in
Vienna.
>> It so happened that Vienna was the only
European capital where dance halls
allowed the walls.
When the nobles saw it, they wanted to
try it. The kings and the princes and
all the aristocratic society find the
love for that dance. They enjoyed it
and once they started walsing they felt
a new sensation. [music]
>> So what sensation did you get when you
were winging?
>> I mean I think it's going very fast and
and you see all around moving. So it's
[music] really like you feel in another
place. Do you remember on the
playgrounds in your when you were very
young and you had those those things
where you could put yourself onto and
turn around turn around pretty much like
this?
>> It is the most exciting experience that
you can have when you are dancing
because you are floating across the
floor and it's really giving you some
feeling like you are a little bit high.
>> After the nobles experienced the walts,
the mood of the negotiations changed.
The prince lolinia was asked how is the
congress going and he said congress is
not going it's dancing.
Dancing certainly contributed to an
atmosphere where the people were able to
make [music] decisions without hatred.
The congress of Vienna produced a peace
agreement and the nobles went home to
teach their nations the walts.
The walts became a dance which was
accepted by the noble society and could
be danced by everyone.
In the decades to come, the Vienna Wals
would become wildly popular throughout
Europe, propelled by the seductive waltz
melodies of Johan Strauss.
Once a journalist attended a ball and he
saw how much the young people were
excited by the music of Yuan Strauss,
how they dance and he went home and and
wrote on the next day in the journal how
many children must be grateful to Yanch
that they exist because after such a
ball young babies were produced by the
excited parents.
So the church had it right all along.
You never know what will happen when a
couple starts to alt.
It is often said that [music] family is
the most important thing.
But to the family whose wealth and power
are [music] on display in the constesses
museum, it was everything.
The Hapsburg [music] family with
branches in Austria and Spain believed
they were God's gift.
constructed genealogies [music] back to
yeah Julius Caesar of course but also
back to the the ancient [music]
Jewish kings to David and Solomon and so
on.
Historian Carl Vulka believes the
Hapsburg used religious relics to cement
their hold on power.
[music]
They laid claim to this lance said to
have pierced Christ on the cross
to prove to themselves [music] and
others that their family was blessed by
the Lord.
The Habsburg [music] themselves were
very convinced that they are the best
ruling family ever.
Full stop.
>> But as everyone knows, pride comes
before a fall.
In the heart of Vienna, underneath an
ancient monastery, is a vast crypt
containing 13 generations of Hapsburg
emperors.
All of us have to go sometime, but the
dates on these coffins reveal something
surprising.
Many are from the 18th century, fewer
from the 19th, and only a handful date
from the 20th century.
What happened to the Hapsburgs?
That is our museum secret.
Francisco Sabalos believes there are
clues in the picture gallery.
Starting with this [music] likeness of
King Carlos II.
The king's priests thought he was
bewitched.
As a geneticist, Francisco thinks
otherwise.
Today we know that inbreeding can cause
unhealthy traits to build up in DNA. But
the Habsburgs didn't. In fact, they
thought marrying within their family
would strengthen the royal bloodline.
The Habsburgs had a very strict rule.
Who is possible partner for a female or
male Habsburg? uh they have to come out
of a former ruling family or of some
clearly defined aristocratic families
that were seen as equal.
As their family tree grew in on itself,
genetic problems became visible in the
facial deformity now known as the
Hapsburg jaw.
But their most severe problem cannot be
seen.
In the family crypt, tracing the
genealogy reveals that many Hapsburgs
[music] died without producing children.
The family was dying out and they knew
it.
They prayed to God to lift the curse
that had befallen them.
And then in 1651,
this little girl was born.
>> Here we have three portraits of
Margarita Teresa. [music] She was a
perfectly normal girl. She was
intelligent and beautiful.
>> At the age of 15, Margarita married
another healthy Hapsburg,
her uncle, Emperor Leupold I.
The family was certain these noble
equals would produce a healthy heir.
Her first child lived just one year. Her
second child survived but died young.
Her next two children were born with
serious genetic abnormalities.
Both died in infancy. [screaming]
Margarita herself would die in pregnancy
when she was only 21.
In the centuries that followed, the
Hapsburgs would avert extinction when a
few broke with tradition to marry
outside the family.
The last claimant to the throne, Ottovon
Hapsburg, was just a child during World
War I when Hapsburg power was crushed on
the battlefield.
He died in 2011 as a private citizen at
the ripe old age of 98.
His funeral procession through Vienna
attracted a 100,000 people, a testament
to the abiding power of the Hapsburg
name in the Austrian imagination.
500 years after their empire began, Otto
was laid to rest among his ancestors.
Perhaps [music] in the hereafter, he'll
wear a crown.
In this museum filled with the
Hapsburg's greatest treasures, for every
mystery we reveal, far more must remain
unspoken.
Secrets of wealth
and power
and of the human heart
hidden in plain sight
inside the constricious museum. Deal.
Heat.
[music]